Guide to the Records of the A/P/A Voices A COVID-19 Public Memory Project TAM.837
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Mock, Emily, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_52
  In this interview, Mock discusses her work as the Chinatown Tenant Union (CTU) Membership Organizer for CAAAV: Organizing Asian Communities. She shares images of tenants organizing before and after the COVID-19 lock-down; and the challenges they met mobilizing around Cancel Rent campaigns and Rent Strikes during the pandemic. Mock talks about the impact of COVID-19 on residents of Chinatown; language justice issues; the use of graphic aids and art in the form of banner drops; and social messaging during social distancing protocols. Prior to the lock down, Mock explains how CTU organizing committee members met every Sunday and held office hours where residents could bring in their leases or get legal assistance; and members also engaged in door knocking twice a week to check on residents. After the lock down, these systems disappeared and the tenants began using WeChat to communicate with each other. Mock discusses the ways tenants have adapted to social distancing and shares the difficulty, and necessity, of talking to Chinese tenants about anti-black racism and Black Lives Matter (BLM). The interview concludes with Mock reflecting on ways small businesses and restaurants in Chinatown have been heavily impacted and forced to close during the pandemic.
  Emily Mock is an artist, educator, and community organizer. Mock is originally from San Francisco, CA and as of 2020, lives in New York City. As of 2020, she is the Chinatown Tenants Union (CTU) Membership Organizer at CAAAV: Organizing Asian Communities; and has created community arts education and public programming as the Center for Neighborhood Leadership Community Organizing Apprentice at The Laundromat Project. She has facilitated in English and Mandarin with all ages in schools, parks, museums, and organizing spaces. Emily is also a member of the Chinatown Art Brigade.
- Morimoto, Risa, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_53
  Materials include a video of Risa Morimoto discussing her father, Hisanori Morimoto, and his death from COVID-19 on April 23, 2020 while living in a nursing home. This was a YouTube video on Morimoto's website, www.ThisIsModernAging.com, which was published on May 7, 2020.
  Risa Morimoto is the founder and CEO of www.ThisIsModernAging.com.
- Morrar, Maisa, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_54
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Loubna Qutami on January 14, 2021. In this interview, Maisa Morrar addresses the pandemic from the perspective of a first responder and discusses the challenges first responders have been experiencing since the beginning of the pandemic. Next, Morrar discusses the historical, racial, and economic inequities that have made certain communities -- particularly Black communities -- more vulnerable and disenfranchised during the pandemic. Morrar illustrates that though the pandemic has resulted in crises of paramount proportions, it also posits new opportunities to envision alternative visions and strategies for health, wellness, and medicine. Morrar examines the work she has done as part of the Oakland Power Project, which works to create and offer resources to the community on alternatives to having to call the police; and mechanisms to develop community-based emergency response that do not further criminalize mental health and disability. Morrar also discusses the struggle Arab-American communities have faced in acquiring relevant data and resources as a result of their census-less status both prior and during the pandemic. Finally, Morrar discusses how the pandemic has posed serious struggles in places like Palestine where people continue to live under a military occupation.
  Maisa Morrar is a physician assistant in Urgent Care and Family Medicine in Oakland, CA. Morrar is also active with the Palestinian Youth Movement, the Palestinian Feminist Collective, and Critical Resistance's Oakland Power Project.
- Na, Taiyo, 2020-2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_55
  Materials include Taiyo Na's poem "Weeks in the Womb" and an audio recording of the poem; an essay "Outlive Us All" by Na; and song lyrics, production information, and a video for the song "We Belong," which was written by Na and Magnetic North in 2010.
- Nabulsi, Mohammed, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_56
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Loubna Qutami on August 25, 2020. In his interview, Mohammed Nabulsi details the impact of the pandemic on the Arab-American community in Houston, TX; the response of state and non-state actors; and the lessons learned and challenges experienced in developing modules for grassroots mutual aid efforts. Nabulsi speaks to the political activism his community has undertaken against anti-Black state violence following the murder of George Floyd; the community's response to the Trump Administration's declaration of the "Deal of the Century"; and the impending Israeli annexation of large portions of the West Bank. Nabulsi details how and why the community is responding to mounting crises; and the challenges they are enduring while also shedding light on the way compassion, care, love and wellness characterize the volunteer lead efforts.
  Mohammed Nabulsi is an attorney and Palestinian community organizer based in Houston, TX. Nabulsi is the national U.S. Vice General Coordinator for the Palestinian Youth Movement (PYM), a member of the board of directors of the Houston-based Palestinian American Cultural Center (PACC), and the General Coordinator for the Houston Arab Community Mutual Aid Coalition (HACMAC). During the COVID-19 global pandemic, Nablusi was a central anchor in a variety of Houston based mutual aid services, political mobilizations, and actions.
- Nguyen, Jessie, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_57
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Sarah Nguyen on June 23, 2021. In the interview, Jessie Nguyen discusses how they wanted to keep their cafe open through the pandemic, but ultimately closed on March 20, 2020, and have remained closed since. Initially, the cafe was able to get funds through small business loans like the Paycheck Protection Program (PPP) and grants provided by the state of California, but Nguyen remembers this process as confusing, involved, and inaccessible to someone who did not have computer literacy or extensive business records.
  As their employees found work elsewhere, the cafe became involved in several community food programs around the city, like SF New Deal, a company made in response to COVID-19 that commissioned small businesses for community meals for COVID-19 shelters. Additionally, utilizing extra equipment no longer used after the cafe shut down, Nguyen started two community fridges and modeled these community fridges off of the Playground Coffee fridge system in Brooklyn, NY. Nguyen felt that in San Francisco and Oakland, many realized that community needs were not being met and had felt a call to action.
  Nguyen also discusses changes to their personal life; and being able to find community outside of their restaurant work, having joined a queer trans Viet healing circle through the QTViet Cafe, a queer trans Viet gathering space in San Francisco. Through this healing circle, Nguyen also developed a three-look collection of clothing called Áo Dài for the Modern Prince. When looking forward, Nguyen states they want to approach any kind of return to restaurant work slowly and in fact, they are unsure if their relationship to food will return as a business since the old cafe structure was, in retrospect, tiring and unsustainable for their mother and themselves.
  Jessie Nguyen is a queer Vietnamese small business owner based in San Francisco, CA. They owned a small cafe in Telegraph Hill with their mother. During the pandemic, after the closure of their cafe, Nguyen developed a three-look collection of clothing called Áo Dài for the Modern Prince that reimagined the traditional Vietnamese áo dài through a diasporic, futuristic, and queer lens.
- Nguyễn, Nguyên Khôi, 2020
  Nguyên Khôi Nguyễn is a multi-disciplinary artist and educator. He is the author of the multimedia graphic novel, The Gulf. He is the vocalist, pianist, composer, and bandleader of the jazz trio, Superior Cling. As of 2020, Nguyên was a digital media lecturer at Loyola University Maryland.
  Materials include a physical and digital copy of Bittersweet: A Pandemic Sketchbook, which recounts the pandemic experience of Nguyên Khôi Nguyễn as he drove from his home in Maryland to reunite with his mother living in Florida, and their journey back to Maryland together.
  - Paper Files (Box Shared Tamiment 189, Folder 6)
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_837_ER_58
- NoDutDol, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_59
  Based in New York City, NoDutDol is a community of North and South Koreans living in the United States. NoDutDol represents the Korean diaspora spread throughout the globe and is made up of artists, filmmakers, teachers, students, workers, professionals, and young families who believe in social justice.
  Materials include two zines: "From Quarantine, With Love: A NDD Zine on Hope in Uncertain Times" and "제국의 제재, Sanctions of Empire."
  "From Quarantine, With Love" is a zine that Jeong Eun Annabel We directed and created. It is a documentation of NoDutDol members' experiences during the COVID-19 Pandemic from late April to early May 2020, and proposes the grassroots organization's collective vision of reunification and demilitarization shaped by the members' reflections on the pandemic.
  "제국의 제재, Sanctions of Empire" is a zine that explores the human impacts of sanctions, particularly as it relates to North Korea. With the pandemic, sanctions on North Korea deepened scarcity, highlighting the imperial motivations of international restrictions when people needed equipment, personal protective equipment, and supplies the most. This zine provides this context.
- Oye, Derek Isawo, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_60
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on July 18, 2020. In this interview, Derek Isawo Oye explains the significance of taiko to the Asian American community and how it has fostered community building. He shares his personal experiences with different Taiko groups; how COVID-19 has impacted the taiko community both financially and as a communal practice; and how remote learning has changed the way the art form is being taught and performed now, and possibly into the future. Oye talks about his concerns for the future of Taiko, an art form that needs to be practiced "in community." The interview concludes with Oye addressing the ways in which the Taiko Community Alliance is addressing Black Lives Matter and issues of equity and diversity across the organization.
  Derek Isawo Oye is a fourth generation Japanese American born and raised in Torrance, CA. He is, as of 2020, the Chair to the Board of Directors of the Taiko Community Alliance, a cultural arts service organization that empowers the people and supports the art of taiko, or Japanese drumming. He is also a member of the seminal North American taiko ensemble, Kinnara Taiko, and an active volunteer at the Gardena Valley Japanese Cultural Institute.
- Park, Danny, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_61
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Crystal (Mun-Hye) Balk on July 14, 2020. In his interview, Danny Park shares his experiences living and working in Los Angeles' Skid Row district -- a space in Los Angeles just adjacent to and overlapping with downtown Los Angeles, Little Tokyo, and the Arts District. Skid Row has the heaviest concentration of homeless people in the United States, and when asked to describe what it has been like working in Skid Row since the pandemic, Park describes the isolation, anxieties, and stresses associated with witnessing the heightened precarity of communities, which are overwhelmingly Black and Brown. Park explains how this community is also already vulnerable with regards to food, healthcare, and shelter access. Park describes the pandemic as a time of deep reflection as he engages his own diasporic family histories and relationships. Park shares what has provided joy and sustenance during this tumultuous moment and the supportive mentorship he has received primarily from Black movement leaders and mentors.
  Danny Park is a social justice-minded small family business owner and community organizer from Los Angeles, CA. As of 2020, he was the owner of Skid Row People's Market and the co-founder of Skid Row Coffee in Los Angeles. Park, who co-manages the market with his mother, May Park, partnered with the Los Angeles Food Policy Council through the Healthy Neighborhood Market Network (HNMN) program with the goal of transitioning the business to focus on healthy food. As a small business owner, Park is deeply involved in the life of the Skid Row neighborhood, advocating for rights to housing, food, and work opportunities. His activism inspired his desire to use his family's market for an even greater purpose.
- Park, Kyoung H., 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_62
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Minju Bae on May 12, 2021. As an artist born in Chile, rooted in Korean diasporas, and living in New York, Kyoung Park highlights the importance of war, militarism, and traumas in his art practice; and discusses his experience as a playwright during the COVID-19 pandemic. Although categorized as "non-essential," culture workers, performers, and artists were left with inadequate relief, pay, or support, but Park worked to raise and distribute mutual aid. He also engaged in healing practices and developed programming around dismantling white supremacy. Park also described how his ensemble worked in virtual platforms, hoping to redefine and decenter theater audiences, and play productions. As a playwright committed to transformative change and abolitionist politics, Park questioned the efficacy of the traditional theater as a means to reach broad audiences, and communicate theses around peace and liberation.
  Kyoung Park is a playwright, performance artist, and theater performer. Park was born in Santiago, Chile and is the first Korean playwright from Latin America to be produced and published in the United States. As of 2021, he is the Artistic Director of Kyoung's Pacific Beat, a peacemaking theater collective that works against oppressions and seeks to heal, uplift, build, and transform the world anew. As Artistic Director, Park writes and directs devised theater by collaborating with artists, non-artists, and local communities to rigorously explore sources of violence, transforming personal and communal experiences of oppression into peace messages made public through performance. Some of Park's works include DISORIENTED, TALA, and PILLOWTALK.
- Ports, Suki Terada, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_63
  Materials include transcript and audio files from oral history interviews conducted by Tomie Arai on June 26, 2020 and June 29, 2020. In her June 26, 2020 interview, Suki Terada Ports shares her family history and talks about how she became an activist; her work in the public school her children attended; and her involvement in community empowerment issues to ensure housing and park land were protected from institutional expansion. She also describes her efforts to provide care for Black, Indigenous, and people of color (BIPOC) communities with HIV/AIDS through the formation of organizations like Asian Pacific Islander Coalition on HIV/AIDS (APICHA).
  In her June 29, 2020 interview, Ports speaks more directly about the personal impact of COVID-19 and sheltering-in-place during the pandemic. She describes mutual aid efforts provided to Japanese American seniors through the Japanese American Association (JAA), where she serves on the Board of Directors.
  Suki Terada Ports has held leadership positions in the Japanese American Citizens League and the Japanese American Association in New York. Ports co-founded the Asian Pacific Islander Coalition on HIV/AIDS (APICHA) and through this organization has been able to assist members of the Asian American community with HIV/AIDS. As the child of parents directly affected by U.S. policies against Japanese Americans during World War II, Ports has devoted herself to improving the quality of life of Japanese Americans. As of 2020, Ports is retired and lives in Manhattan.
- Queens Mutual Aid Network: Rima Begum & Moumita Ahmed, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_64
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Cynthia Gao on July 16, 2020. In the interview, Rima Begum and Moumita Ahmed explain how Queens Mutual Aid (QMA) was founded, how it was run, and what kinds of community assistance was provided. QMA's central work was food distribution; and the logistical processes of intake, fulfillment, and delivery are described. The importance of cultural sensitivity and its relationship to mutual aid principles; questions of morality and ethics amidst overwhelming need; and spiking COVID-19 deaths are also discussed.
  Ahmed discusses her understanding of mutual aid; the importance of accessibility through language and computer literacy; and her political inspirations. Ahmed describes working and collaborating with other mutual aid projects in the city such as Astoria Mutual Aid, Sunnyside Mutual Aid, and the Ridgewood Tenants Union. She discusses her belief that many COVID-19 related deaths in the Bangladeshi community were under-reported or unrecorded by the city as a consequence of racial misclassification and language barriers. Although many Bangladeshis are also essential workers, despite their growing population, Bangladeshis do not have meaningful representation in local politics and are often lumped in with other "model minority" Asian American groups.
  Begum discusses her day job with Chhaya Community Development Corporation and her experiences working with tenants trying to navigate rent relief programs, rent strikes, and difficult landlords. Ahmed discusses the challenges of mounting a political campaign for district leader, which she lost by sixty votes, in the middle of a pandemic. These challenges included contracting a mild case of COVID-19 and being a candidate of color operating outside the local party machine.
  Rima Begum and Moumita Ahmed were lead organizers of Queens Mutual Aid (QMA), an ad hoc mutual aid project that ran from March 2020 to June 2020. They are both Bangladeshi-American and work with Bangladeshi Americans for Progress. Begum is also a tenant organizer with Chhaya Community Development Corporation, a Queens non-profit, which works on behalf of South Asian and Indo-Caribbean communities. Ahmed was a candidate for female district leader for Assembly 24 in 2020 and ran for City Council in District 24 in 2021.
- Quenga, Kaina, 2021
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_837_ER_65
    Materials include a transcript from an oral history interview conducted by Crystal (Mun-Hye) Balk on February 28, 2021. In this interview, Kaina Quenga talks at length about the different ways the pandemic has impacted the Hawaiian economy and community. Quenga explains that despite the economic challenges performing artists faced during lockdown, she managed to continue teaching remotely throughout the pandemic and took a traditional chanting class. Quenga recalls both the refreshing experience of being in Hawai'i without tourists at the beginning of lockdown and the frustrating experience of tourists returning, some with ideas of relocating permanently or even buying property to develop in Hawai'i. She recalls the fear Native Hawaiians faced during the pandemic due to the Indigenous population's history with invasive and deadly disease.
    Quenga describes how the Indigenous communities, in and outside of Hawai'i, have organized throughout the pandemic with solidarity and support. She talks about Protect Mauna Kea and her work with Nā ʻOiwi NYC, a group that educates about Indigenous Hawaiian culture. She also discusses working with groups like the Indigenous Peoples Day Coalition and the A/P/A Institute to continue her mission to educate about the struggles and culture of Indigenous Hawai'i; and support Indigenous peoples across the United States.
    The transcript of this oral history interview can be accessed in the NYU Special Collections reading room or remotely.
    Kaina Quenga is an Indigenous and Native Hawaiian, as well as professional hula dancer and instructor. She was based in Hilo, Hawai'i at the time of the interview. The narrator had spent the last 20 years living in New York, but moved back to Hawai'i in January of 2020.
- Richards, Zabrina, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_66
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Rochelle Kwan on September 6, 2020. A drawing titled "Go Back to China" and poems by Zabrina Richards are also included.
  In this interview, Richards talks about her experience as an Asian American adoptee living in the predominantly white town of Arundel, Maine, where she lacks an Asian American community. Since the start of the pandemic, Richards has been particularly focused on the news of xenophobia and hate crimes against Asians and Asian Americans. She recalls her mother's decision to not allow her to go grocery shopping because she did not want Richards to be the next potential target of a hate crime. For Richards, the pandemic has revealed the detrimental impacts of the model minority myth, the discrimination Asian Americans continue to face in the U.S. today, and the fear of violence for being Asian American. To cope with these fears and frustrations, Richards has been spending her time reading, writing poetry, and learning about Asian American history. In the future, she hopes to connect with other Asian American youth through her poetry, organizing, and celebrating of their Asian American identity and culture.
  Zabrina Richards is a Chinese American, first generation, transracially adopted high school student from Arundel, Maine.
- Rongkilyo, Set Hernandez, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_67
  Materials include a transcript from an oral history interview conducted by Crystal (Mun-Hye) Balk on August 24, 2020. In the interview, Set Hernandez Rongkilyo shares their thoughts about what it means to navigate COVID-19 in Los Angeles, CA as a Black, Indigenous, and Person of Color (BIPOC); queer; and undocumented person. They mention that COVID-19 is not the worst thing they've experienced because shelter-in-place conditions are something they and other undocumented peoples experience on a daily basis beyond the pandemic. Rongkilyo discusses their cultural work and labor as a filmmaker; and how important and grounding their work has been, especially during difficult or sad moments.
  Rongkilyo reflects on the importance of supporting the Black Lives Matter (BLM) uprisings and the Black community. Rongkilyo shares how they came out to their mother during the pandemic; their methods of communication with their father, who lives in the Philippines; being reunited with someone who took care of them and their siblings in the Philippines when their parents were migrant workers in Japan; and the passing of a migrant worker and fellow community organizer from COVID-19 in June 2020. Rongkilyo reflects on the complex meaning of "value" when it comes to the lives of migrant workers, undocumented peoples, and others who inhabit precarious social positions; and how certain people might come to believe that their lives are less "significant" than others.